A Guide to the Papers of [Francis] Coleman Rosenberger, 1946-1952
Special Collections Department, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Papers of [Francis] Coleman Rosenberger, 1946-1952
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
5719
This collection consists of 163 items.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
This collection was a gift from F. Coleman Rosenberger of Alexandria, Virginia, on 1957 October 31.
Biographical/Historical Information
Coleman Rosenberger was born March 22, 1915, in Manassas, Virginia. He attended the University of Virginia and received an LL.B. degree from George Washington University in 1942. Rosenberger was an attorney, writer, and editor. Rosenberger published several volumes of his own poetry: The Virginia Poems (Gotham Book Mark, 1943), XII Poems (Gotham Book Mart, 1946), One Season Here (University Press of Virginia, 1946), An Alphabet (University Press of Virginia, 1978), and The Visit (Tabula Rasa Press, 1984). A selection of the books he edited includes: Virginia Reader: a Treasury of Writings from the First Voyage to the Present (Dutton, 1948; reprinted Octagon, 1972), American Sampler: a Selection of Poetry (Prairie Press, 1951), Jefferson Reader: a Treasury of Writings about Thomas Jefferson (Dutton, 1953), Records of the Columbia Historical Society of Washington, D.C. (8 vols., University Press of Virginia, 1961-1980), Washington and the Poet (an anthology, University Press of Virginia, 1977).
Rosenberger also contributed poetry to 5 anthologies during the 1940s and contributed poetry to approximately 40 periodicals. He was a book reviewer for the Richmond Times-Dispatch (1938-1940), Washington Post (1940-1945), New York Herald Tribune Book Review (195-1962), and Washington Star (1967-1971). He was also interested in genealogy and wrote Some Notes on the Rosenberger Family in Pennsylvania & Virginia, 1729-1950 (William Byrd Press, 1950), and edited The Robinson-Rosenberger Journey to the Gold Fields of California, 1849-1850: the Diary of Zirkle D. Robinson (Prairie Press, 1966).
Rosenberger received a National Poetry Center Award at the New York World's Fair in 1939.
Rosenberger was admitted to the Virginia bar in 1939, bar of the U.S. Supreme Court in 1949, and was a member of the legal and legislative staff of the U.S. Senate, 1942-1978. He received a certificate of commendation for scholarly editing from the American Association for State and Local History in 1971 for his work on the Records of the Columbia Historical Society of Washington, D.C.
Scope and Content Information
This literary collection of Francis Coleman Rosenberger (1915-) consists of 163 items, 1946-1952, with most of the items dating from 1946-1948. The collection primarily includes letters and poems to Coleman Rosenberger in response to his inquiry to current American poets for "new poems which have not previously appeared in print." These poems were for the column, "A Selection of Recent American Poetry" for the British publication, Poetry Quarterly, edited by Wrey Gardiner. Rosenberger was aiming for a selection which would " show something of the variety and the worth of poetry in the United States to-day." Rosenberger's selections were published in 2 issues: v. 8, no. 4 (Winter 1946-47), and v. 9, no. 3 (Autumn 1947). Rosenberger collected poems from more poets than were published in these issues. Only poems selected by Rosenberger are in this manuscript collection; poets sometimes write they are sending a specific number of poems, which are greater than the number in the collection.
A small portion of the collection concerns the use of the poems for "American Sampler: a selection of new poetry," edited by Rosenberger.
The Coleman Rosenberger Literary Collection includes poems, most of which are typed manuscripts. Some manuscripts are signed, and some are drafts containing handwritten corrections.
The Collection also contains letters or postcards from the following poets, saying that they did not have any poems to contribute: Louise Bogan, Gwendolyn Brooks, Katherine Garrison Chapin, E. E. Cummings, Lawrence Lee, Marianne Moore, Delmore Schwartz, Winfield Townley Scott, Allen Tate, Reed Whittemore, and Oscar Williams.
Several letters from Kenneth Durant concerning the poetry of Genevieve Taggard are in the Collection. Some of these are about the texts of her poems; others are about securing copies of her manuscripts and publications for the Genevieve Taggart Collection at Dartmouth College Library.
Also included in the Collection are two letters from C. Wrey Gardiner concerning the publication of American poetry in the Poetry Quarterly including the amount paid for the poems.
A letter from Helen Stewart asks permission to reprint Mark Van Doren's poems, which appeared in Poetry Quarterly, in an anthology of his works.
A letter from Geraldine Udell of Poetry requested whether she could order a copy of Poetry Quarterly from Rosenberger.
Letters from Gore Vidal accompanying his poems are included although none of his poems are in the Collection.
Contents List
- Poetry of Francis Coleman Rosenberger
  - John Malcolm Brinnin:
    - "Faces, Faces"
    - "Holiday of Sleep" (2 versions)
  - Richard Eberhart: "The Full Weakness of Man"
  - Frederick Ebright: "Last Supper"
  - Robert E. Hayden: "A Ballad of Remembrance"
  - Langston Hughes: "Summer Evening: Calumet Avenue: Chicago"
  - Rolfe Humphries "Hell"
  - Randall Jarrell: "The Place of Death"
  - Weldon Kees:
    - "A Good Chord and a Bad Piano"
    - "River Song"
  - Coman Leavenworth: "Victory in Europe"
  - Ruth Lechlitner: "To That Far Future"
  - Eve Merriam: "The Clever Story"
  - Josephine Miles:
    - "Eagle"
    - "Laurel"
    - "Prospecter"
  - Howard Moss: "Around the Fish: After Paul Klee"
  - Kenneth Patchen: "Three Poems:"
    - "Beings so Hideous That the Air Weeps Blood"
    - "The Stars Go to Sleep So Peacefully"
    - "Summer Day"
  - Selden Rodman: "Circeron"
  - Karl Shapiro: "An Urn of Ashes"
  - Theodore Spencer:
    - "New England Marriage"
    - "Poem"
    - "Song"
    - "Temptation Resisted"
  - Wallace Stevens: "Memorandum", 2 copies: one typed, one handwritten.
  - Mark Van Doren:
    - "False Summer"
    - "The Sun So Old"
  - Byron Vazakas:
    - "Resurrection"
    - "Silent Film"
    - "T.B."
  - Richard Wilbur:
    - "Bell Speech"
    - "Ceremony"
    - "The Death of a Toad"
    - "L'Etoile (Degas, 1876)"
    - "First Snow in Alsace"
    - "For Ellen"
    - "The Giaour and the Pacha (Eugene Delacroix, 1856)
    - "Natural Song"
    - "Poplar, Sycamore"
    - "The Waters"
  - William Carlos Williams:
    - "Education is a Failure"
    - "The Quality of Heaven"
  - Marya Zaturenska:
    - "The Gray Room"
    - "Perdita's Song"
- Letters and Postcards
  - Copies of Poetry Quarterly and advertisements 1946-[1951], Printed
  - Louise Bogan 1946 Aug 8, ALS
  - John Malcolm Brinnin, with drafts of poems 1946 & 1948, 4TLS, 3TMs
  - Gwendolyn Brooks 1946 Nov 30, TLS
  - Katherine Garrison Chapin 1946 Aug 1, TLS
  - E. E. Cummings 1946 Aug 23, TLS
  - Kenneth Durant 1949, 1950 & 1952, 8TLS
  - 2TLS, TMs 1946 & 1948, Richard Eberhart, with poem
  - Frederick Ebright, with poem 1946-1948 & 1951, 6TLS, APCS, TMs
  - Paul Engle 1946 Aug 11, TPCS
  - Charles Wrey Gardiner 1946 & 1947, 2ALS
  - Robert E. Hayden, with poem 1946 & 1948, 3TLS, TMs, APCS
  - Langston Hughes, with poem 1946-1948, 5TLS, TMs
  - Rolfe Humphries, with poem 1946 Aug 1, TLS, TMs
  - Randall Jarrell, with poem [1947]-1948, 2ALS, TMs
  - Weldon Kees, with 2 poems 1946, 1948 & 1952, TLS, 2ALS, 3 PCS, 2TMs
  - Coman Leavenworth, with poem 1948 Aug 13, TLS, TMs
  - Ruth Lechlitner, with poem 1946-1948, ALS, 2TLS, TPCs, TMs
  - Lawrence Lee 1946, 3TLS
  - Eve Merriam, one poem only 1946 Sep 3, TMsS
  - Josephine Miles, with 3 poems 1946 & 1948, 3ALS, 3TMs
  - Marianne Moore 1946, 2TLS
  - Howard Moss, with poem 1946, 1948 & 1949, 4TLS, TMs
  - Kenneth Patchen, with 3 poems 1946 & 1948, ALS, TLS, AMsS
  - Selden Rodman, with poem 1946, 2ALS, APCS, TMs
  - Delmore Schwartz 1946 Jul 24, APCS
  - Winfield Townley Scott 1946 Aug 22, TLS
  - Karl Shapiro, with 1 poem 1946 & [1948], 2ALS, 2 APCS, TMs
  - Theodore Spencer, with 4 poems 1946 Jul 26, ALS, 3TMsS, TMs
  - Wallace Stevens, with drafts of poem 1946 & 1948, 3TLS, TMsS, AMsS
  - Helen Stewart 1947 Mar 3, TLS
  - Allen Tate 1946, 2TLS
  - Geraldine Udell 1947 Oct 27, TLS
  - Mark Van Doren, with 2 poems 1946-1948, ALS, 3APCS, 2TMs
  - Byron Vazakas, with 3 poems 1946, 1948 & 1951, 6TLS, 3TPCS, 3TMs
  - Gore Vidal 1946, 2TLS
  - Robert Penn Warren 1946 Aug 13, TLS
  - Reed Whittemore 1946 Aug 19, TPCS
  - Richard Wilbur, with 10 poems 1946-1948, 2TLS, 4ALS, 10 TMsS, APCS, TPCS
  - Oscar Williams 1946 Jul 31, TLS
  - William Carlos Williams, with 2 poems 1946 & 1948, 2ANS, 2TMsS
  - Marya Zaturenska, with 2 poems 1946 & 1948, ALS, APCS, TMsS